<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
>

<channel>
	<title>Humour &#8211; Anshul Khare</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2019 13:09:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>https://i2.wp.com/anshulkhare.in/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/cropped-favicon-2.png?fit=32%2C32&#038;ssl=1</url>
	<title>Humour &#8211; Anshul Khare</title>
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">157338388</site>	<item>
		<title>The Epiphany</title>
		<link>./../../../the-epiphany/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../the-epiphany/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshul Khare]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 08 Jan 2019 04:39:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Humour]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false"></guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>“See, when you want to reverse the car to left, you have to turn the steering wheel to the left,” I told my wife. She was learning reverse parking and I was her self-appointed driving coach. “But when I turn left, the car is going towards right!” she exclaimed. “No! The car is going towards [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../the-epiphany/index.html">The Epiphany</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>“See, when you want to reverse the car to left, you have to turn the steering wheel to the left,” I told my wife. She was learning reverse parking and I was her self-appointed driving coach.</p>
<p>“But when I turn left, the car is going towards right!” she exclaimed.</p>
<p><span id="more-1"></span></p>
<p>“No! The car is going towards left. See, the left tail lamp is going left,” I showed her in the side view mirror.</p>
<p>“Yeah but the right headlamp is going towards the right,” she pointed towards the right headlamp which appeared to be moving towards right from driving seat. Of course, it had to. If you are focusing on the front, the nose of the car will seem to go towards the right.</p>
<p>“But why are you focusing on the front headlamp? When you’re reversing your point of reference should be the tail lamp,” I explained.</p>
<p>“Then why didn’t you explicitly tell me that before?” she asked almost in complete frustration.</p>
<p>“I thought you would…,” before I could complete my sentence, I had an epiphany.</p>
<p>We were both right about “where the car was going.” But our definitions of “where the car was going” were inconsistent. She was looking forward while reversing the car like many amateur drivers do, while I assumed that she was looking back.</p>
<p>“You know, you’re right.” I said that with a great sense of relief.</p>
<p>What did I learn that day?</p>
<p>All misunderstandings happen because at some level people start with inconsistent assumptions and fail to communicate it.</p>
<p>No. No. That’s all self-help-feel-good hokum.</p>
<p>What I really learned or rather re-learned that day was &#8211; Very few people are always right. Your wife is one of them.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../the-epiphany/index.html">The Epiphany</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../the-epiphany/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">1</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Scam of Percentages</title>
		<link>./../../../scam-of-percentages/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../scam-of-percentages/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshul Khare]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 04:23:01 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Humour]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://demo.athemes.com/sydney/?p=137</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The day remains clearly etched in my memory. I was in fifth standard and one day I came home utterly dejected. The maths teacher had introduced the concept of percentages and I just couldn’t fathom it. It sounded freakishly alien. I literally had tears in my eyes because it seemed that everybody in the class [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../scam-of-percentages/index.html">The Scam of Percentages</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The day remains clearly etched in my memory. I was in fifth standard and one day I came home utterly dejected. The maths teacher had introduced the concept of percentages and I just couldn’t fathom it. It sounded freakishly alien. I literally had tears in my eyes because it seemed that everybody in the class understood it except me.</p>
<p>The teacher had repeated the definition &#8211; percentage is when you convert any ratio into base of hundred &#8211; at least a dozen times in the class that day. It didn’t help.</p>
<p><span id="more-137"></span></p>
<p>Then my father explained, “Look. When you divide something into two equal parts, each part is called half, right? Instead of calling it half, let’s call it 50 percent. Now, when you divide something into four equal parts each portion is one fourth, correct? Let’s call that 25 percent.”</p>
<p>That made some sense. Although it took some time but finally I was able to wrap my head around this strange human invention called percentages.</p>
<p>20 years later, my wife upended the theory of percentages.</p>
<p>“I am 400 percent sure about this.” She would often say and leave the fifth standard kid in me thinking, &#8220;I knew this percentage business was all scam.&#8221;</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../scam-of-percentages/index.html">The Scam of Percentages</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../scam-of-percentages/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">137</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
