<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	
xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:geo="http://www.w3.org/2003/01/geo/wgs84_pos#"
>

<channel>
	<title>Books &#8211; Anshul Khare</title>
	<atom:link href="./index.html" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<description></description>
	<lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2019 07:24:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>https://i2.wp.com/anshulkhare.in/wp-content/uploads/2019/02/cropped-favicon-2.png?fit=32%2C32&#038;ssl=1</url>
	<title>Books &#8211; Anshul Khare</title>
	<link>./../../../index.html</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
<site xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">157338388</site>	<item>
		<title>Edison&#8217;s Muckers, Jeff Bezos, and Decision Paralysis</title>
		<link>./../../../edison-muckers-jeff-bezos-decision-paralysis/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../edison-muckers-jeff-bezos-decision-paralysis/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshul Khare]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 22 Apr 2019 05:28:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Decision Making]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=826</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Excerpt from the book Made to Stick by Chip and Dan Heath Most people in an organization aren’t in charge of formulating strategy; they just have to understand the strategy and use it to make decisions. But many strategies aren’t concrete enough to resolve a well­ established psychological bias called decision paralysis. Psychologists have uncovered [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../edison-muckers-jeff-bezos-decision-paralysis/index.html">Edison&#8217;s Muckers, Jeff Bezos, and Decision Paralysis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Excerpt from the book <a href="https://amzn.to/2Xynajb" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Made to Stick</a> by Chip and Dan Heath</p>
<blockquote><p>Most people in an organization aren’t in charge of formulating strategy; they just have to understand the strategy and use it to make decisions. But many strategies aren’t concrete enough to resolve a well­ established psychological bias called decision paralysis. Psychologists have uncovered situations where the mere existence of choice, even choice among several good options, seems to paralyze us in making decisions.</p></blockquote>
<p>Barry Swartz in his book <a href="https://amzn.to/2PrxUNC" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Paradox of Choice</a> has covered the idea of <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>Decision Paralysis</strong></span> in detail.</p>
<p>Heaths write —</p>
<blockquote><p>Every organization must make choices among attractive options: Customer service versus cost minimization. Revenue growth versus maximizing profitability. Quality versus speed to market. People development versus the needs of the quarter. Mix together lots of these tensions—an atmosphere full of potential opportunities and risks and uncertainties and incomplete information—and you’ve got a recipe for paralysis.</p></blockquote>
<p><span id="more-826"></span></p>
<blockquote><p>Organizations, in formulating their strategies, must grapple not just with competitive advantage but with their internal capabilities. What capabilities do we need in order to grow? What skills will our employees need to successfully please customers, and how will we get better at serving our customers over time? An example of strategic language that speaks to internal capabilities comes from Thomas Alva Edison, the inventor of the phonograph and the light bulb. Edison was not a lone inventor; he created the first industrial R&amp;D lab in Menlo Park, NewJersey. The researchers in his labs were called “<strong><span style="text-decoration: underline;">muckers</span>.</strong>” The term comes from two slang phrases of the time—“<span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>to muck in</strong></span>” was to work together as mates, and “to muck around” was to fool around. Why was this a good way for Edison’s researchers to talk strategy?</p>
<p>In any entrepreneurial organization, there’s a natural tension between efficiency and experimentation. Innovation requires experimentation and freedom, and it necessarily involves dead ends and wasted time and errors—all of which, in turn, will reduce efficiency. Edison’s environment, then, is ripe for decision paralysis: How do we decide between efficiency and experimentation? Efficiency promises reduced costs, better margins, and more orders. Experimentation promises new products and other opportunities. How do you choose in the myriad daily situations where the conflict will arise? (E.g., “Is it okay to spend the next hour of my time fooling around in the lab?”)</p>
<p>The term “muckers” is a strategy statement masquerading as a nickname. It makes it clear that, given the tough choice between efficiency and experimentation, you choose experimentation. Why? Because you’re a mucker. Muckers don’t obsess over Gantt charts. Muckers muck. And muckers muck because that is precisely the organizational capability that will make Menlo Park successful. <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><em><strong>Talking strategy in a thoughtful way can relieve the burden of decision paralysis.</strong></em></span></p></blockquote>
<p>Among all the contemporary business leaders, no one can outdo Jeff Bezos when it comes to communicating and explaining business strategies. He says that <span style="text-decoration: underline;"><strong>high velocity decision making </strong></span>requires a different framework. In his <a href="./../../../wp-content/uploads/2019/04/Amazon-Letter-2015.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">2015 letter to Amazon shareholders</a>, Bezos wrote —</p>
<blockquote><p>There are some decisions which are irreversible. They’re like one way doors. The consequences of these decisions can’t be undone. You have live with them for all your life. Bezos says that such decisions should be made methodically, carefully, slowly and with great deliberations and lot of thought. These are Type 1 decisions.</p>
<p>But most decisions aren’t like Type 1. They are changeable, reversible. They’re two way doors. If you’ve made a suboptimal Type 2 decision, you don’t have to live with the consequences for that long. You can reopen the door and go back through. Type 2 decisions can and should be made quickly.</p>
<p>As the companies become bigger they have a tendency to adopt the Type-1 decision making process for all decisions. As a result, Type 2 decisions also get slow. There’s unnecessary risk aversion and people stop experimenting.</p></blockquote>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../edison-muckers-jeff-bezos-decision-paralysis/index.html">Edison&#8217;s Muckers, Jeff Bezos, and Decision Paralysis</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../edison-muckers-jeff-bezos-decision-paralysis/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">826</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Look What I Avoided for You</title>
		<link>./../../../look-what-i-avoided-for-you/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../look-what-i-avoided-for-you/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshul Khare]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 15 Apr 2019 09:33:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Behaviour]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=813</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>It’s an underlying human tendency to say 'Look what I did for you' than 'Look what I avoided for you.' Conventional wisdom has its roots in all too common psychological biases afflicting the human brain - Social Proof, Incentive caused bias and Illusion of busyness.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../look-what-i-avoided-for-you/index.html">Look What I Avoided for You</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Excerpt from the book <a href="https://amzn.to/2QcH27e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Antifragile</a> —</p>
<blockquote><p>Consider this need to do-something through an illustrative example. In the 1930s, 389 children were presented to New York City doctors; 174 of them were recommended tonsillectomies [surgically removing the tonsil, a small bell shaped piece of organ hanging inside your throat]. The remaining 215 children were again presented to doctors, and 99 were said to need the surgery. When the remaining 116 children were shown to yet a third set of doctors, 52 were recommended the surgery&#8230;note that a death occurs in abo ut every 15000 such operations…every child who undergoes an unnecessary operation has a shortening of her life expectancy.</p>
<p>When you medicate a child for an imagined or invented psychiatric disease, say, ADHD or depression, instead of letting him out of the cage, the long-term harm is largely unaccounted for.</p>
<p>&#8230;the doctor who refrains from operating on a back (a very expensive surgery), instead giving it a chance to heal itself, will not be rewarded and judged as favourably as the doctor who makes the surgery look indispensable, then brings relief to the patient while exposing him to operating risks, while accruing great financial rewards to himself.</p></blockquote>
<p>It’s an underlying human tendency to say &#8216;<em>Look what I did for you&#8217;</em> than &#8216;<em><strong>Look what I avoided for you.&#8217;</strong></em></p>
<p><span id="more-813"></span></p>
<p>An excerpt from the book <a href="https://amzn.to/2UeGkZj" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Think Like A Freak</a> —</p>
<blockquote><p>Based on statistics, for a world class soccer player the chances of converting a penalty kick is 75 percent. To save the goal, keeper has to guess the ball direction and take a leap accordingly. Typically he jumps toward the kicker&#8217;s left corner 57 percentage of the time and to the right only 41. Which means that the goal keeper stays at the middle only 2 out of 100 times. A kick towards center, as risky as it may appear, is 7 percentage points more likely to succeed than a kick to the corner. Still only 17 percent of kicks are aimed at center. If you think about going the traditional route, toward a corner and if the keeper does guess correctly and stops the ball &#8211; well, you have made a valiant effort even if it was bested by a more valiant one. If you follow this selfish incentive &#8211; protecting your own reputation by not doing something potentially foolish &#8211; you are more likely to kick toward a corner. If you follow the communal incentive &#8211; trying to win the game for your nation even though you risk looking personally foolish (a straight kick saved by a goal keeper will give the impression that kicker didn&#8217;t do anything and just threw it in the goal keeper&#8217;s arms) &#8211; you will kick toward the center.</p></blockquote>
<p>This is the case where the illusion of busyness prevails &#8211; where being busy in this context means kicking toward a corner and inaction means kicking the ball straight at the center.</p>
<p>My friend <a href="https://twitter.com/jvembuna" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Jana Vembunarayanan</a> has written an excellent post on this topic &#8211; <a href="http://janav.wordpress.com/2014/07/08/unconventional-wisdom/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Unconventional Wisdom</a>.</p>
<p>Warren Buffett describes this situation in the corporate world &#8211;</p>
<blockquote><p>Most managers have very little incentive to make the “intelligent but with some chance of looking like an idiot decision”. Their personal gain/loss ratio is all too obvious; if an unconventional decision works out well, they get a pat on the back, and if it works out poorly, they get a pink slip. Failing conventionally is the route to go; as a group, lemmings may have a rotten image, but no individual lemming has ever received bad press.</p></blockquote>
<p>Conventional wisdom has its roots in all too common psychological biases afflicting the human brain &#8211; Social Proof, Incentive caused bias and Illusion of busyness.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../look-what-i-avoided-for-you/index.html">Look What I Avoided for You</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../look-what-i-avoided-for-you/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">813</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>A Powerful Persuasion Hack: The Columbo Tactic</title>
		<link>./../../../a-powerful-persuasion-hack-the-columbo-tactic/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../a-powerful-persuasion-hack-the-columbo-tactic/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshul Khare]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 11 Apr 2019 05:24:30 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Behaviour]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=793</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Columbo Tactic is a psychological maneuver used by persuasion experts. It’s a subtle hack that goes unnoticed if one doesn’t know about it but it can get you what they want from others, i.e., compliance.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../a-powerful-persuasion-hack-the-columbo-tactic/index.html">A Powerful Persuasion Hack: The Columbo Tactic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>An excerpt from the book <a href="https://amzn.to/2D8j1Lb" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The McKinsey Way</a> —</p>
<blockquote><p>If you watched TV in the 1970s, you may remember Peter Falk’s trenchcoat-wearing detective, Lieutenant Columbo. After he finished quizzing a murder suspect about her whereabouts on the night in question, he would pick up his rumpled raincoat and head out the door. As he reached the threshold and was about to leave, he would turn around, stick his finger up to his temple, and say, “Excuse me, ma’am, but there’s something I forgot to ask.” This question invariably gave Columbo the answer he needed to figure out who did it.</p>
<p>If there’s a particular question you need to answer to, or a piece of data that you want, the Columbo tactic is often a good way to get it. Once the interview is over, everybody becomes more relaxed. The interviewee’s sense that you have some power over him will have disappeared. He is far less likely to be defensive, and will often tell you what you need or give you the information you seek on the spot. Try it; it works.</p></blockquote>
<p>The Columbo Tactic is a psychological maneuver used by persuasion experts. It’s a subtle hack that goes unnoticed if one doesn’t know about it but it can get you what they want from others, i.e., compliance.</p>
<p>I have been at the receiving end of <strong><em>The Columbo Tactic</em></strong> at least once in my life.</p>
<p>In December 2003, I was resigning from my first job. The Vice President invited me to his cabin for an exit interview. He was obviously concerned because I was leaving the company after spending merely five months. The meeting was done in 20 minutes and I was stepping out of his office. Just when my one foot was out of his cabin, he fired the Columbo shot.</p>
<p>“By the way Anshul, are you sure there is no other reason for leaving the company?”</p>
<p>That was 15 years back but now I can connect the dots. The VP did know a thing or two about human psychology and persuasion tactics.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../a-powerful-persuasion-hack-the-columbo-tactic/index.html">A Powerful Persuasion Hack: The Columbo Tactic</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../a-powerful-persuasion-hack-the-columbo-tactic/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">793</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Investing Insights from Medicine</title>
		<link>./../../../investing-insight-from-medicine/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../investing-insight-from-medicine/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshul Khare]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 19 Feb 2019 09:10:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=634</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I was invited by Bangalore Investor Group to make a presentation. My presentation was based on two books — The Laws of Medicine and Risk Savvy. Both these books were few of the best ones I read in 2018. Two primary ideas that I share in this talk are — Benford&#8217;s Law and Mathematics of Cancer Screening. [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../investing-insight-from-medicine/index.html">Investing Insights from Medicine</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I was invited by Bangalore Investor Group to make a presentation.</p>
<p>My presentation was based on two books — <a href="https://amzn.to/2SbYda2" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Laws of Medicine</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/2KccYq3" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Risk Savvy</a>.</p>
<p>Both these books were few of the best ones I read in 2018.</p>
<p>Two primary ideas that I share in this talk are — Benford&#8217;s Law and Mathematics of Cancer Screening. Here&#8217;s the video version of the talk.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DQMpF6S1Jco" width="560" height="315" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen"></iframe></p>
<p>Please <a href="https://youtu.be/DQMpF6S1Jco" target="_blank" rel="noopener">click here</a> if you can&#8217;t see the video.</p>
<p>Looking forward to your feedback.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../investing-insight-from-medicine/index.html">Investing Insights from Medicine</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../investing-insight-from-medicine/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">634</post-id>	</item>
		<item>
		<title>Unnerving Words of an Idiosyncratic Genius</title>
		<link>./../../../unnerving-words-of-an-idiosyncratic-genius/index.html</link>
					<comments>./../../../unnerving-words-of-an-idiosyncratic-genius/index.html#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Anshul Khare]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 10:31:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Books]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">./../../../index.html?p=466</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Greek mythology has a story about a bandit called Procrustes. His name means “the stretcher.” True to his name, Procrustes was a rogue smith who would abduct travelers, treat them with a lavish dinner and invite them to spend the night in a special bed. He wanted the bed to fit the traveler to perfection, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../unnerving-words-of-an-idiosyncratic-genius/index.html">Unnerving Words of an Idiosyncratic Genius</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Greek mythology has a story about a bandit called Procrustes. His name means “the stretcher.” True to his name, Procrustes was a rogue smith who would abduct travelers, treat them with a lavish dinner and invite them to spend the night in a special bed.</p>
<p>He wanted the bed to fit the traveler to perfection, writes Taleb in his book <a href="https://amzn.to/2SmF0ng" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Bed of Procrustes</a>, “Those who were too tall had their legs chopped off with a sharp hatchet; those who were too short were stretched.”</p>
<p>Nobody ever fitted the bed exactly and Procrustes’ reign of terror continued until he was captured by Theseus who “fitted” Procrustes in his own bed.</p>
<p>A Procrustean solution is thus the practice of forcefully fitting reality to the rigid containers of theoretical models and preconceived structures. This post is a compilation of my highlights and notes from The Bed of Procrustes — Taleb’s lesser known book.</p>
<p><span id="more-466"></span></p>
<p>Nassim Nicholas Taleb is at the top of my list of favourite authors. Look at <a href="./../../../books/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">my favourite books</a> and you’d find Taleb’s <a href="https://amzn.to/2QcH27e" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Antifragile</a> as the first item.</p>
<p>He’s someone who is least bothered about writing best selling books. Taleb has neither any desire nor any regard for things like New York Times best seller list. Ironically, all his books have been smashing hits and he has a cult-like fan following.</p>
<p>Explaining the theme of <em>Procrustean Bed,</em> Taleb writes —</p>
<blockquote><p>We humans, facing limits of knowledge, and things we do not observe, the unseen and the unknown, resolve the tension by squeezing life and the world into crisp commoditized ideas, reductive categories, specific vocabularies, and prepackaged narratives, which on the occasion, has explosive consequences.</p></blockquote>
<p>This book is a collection of aphorisms from Taleb. It could be dangerous to read such books for short sentences can be misinterpreted when the context is missing. Nevertheless, pithy sayings have always been the favoured method of ancient thinkers and philosophers to pack their wisdom.</p>
<p>Taleb again —</p>
<blockquote><p>Aphorisms, maxims, proverbs, short sayings, even, to some extent, epigrams are the earliest literary form &#8211; often integrated into what we now call poetry. They carry the cognitive compactness of the sound bite&#8230;Aphorisms require us to change our reading habits and approach them in small doses; each one of them is a complete unit, a complete narrative dissociated from others.</p></blockquote>
<p>The best part about this book is that Taleb has refrained from adding details to his one-liners.</p>
<p>“If you want to annoy a poet, explain his poetry.” quips Taleb. “Aphorisms lose their charm whenever explained.”</p>
<p>It would annoy him if he finds out that someone (yours truly) tried to add commentary to his aphorisms. So I won&#8217;t do it.</p>
<p>I’ll merely reproduce a small sample of quotes from the book which created fireworks in my brain. I hope they have the same effect on you.</p>
<p>So, get ready for the unnerving words of an idiosyncratic genius.</p>
<hr style="width: 80%;" />
<p><em>To understand the liberating effect of asceticism, consider that losing all your fortune is much less painful than losing only half of it.</em></p>
<p><em>Modernity’s double punishment is to make us both age prematurely and live longer.</em></p>
<p><em>In nature we never repeat the same motion; in captivity (office, gym, commute, sports), life is just repetitive-stress injury. No randomness.</em></p>
<p><em>The test of whether you really liked a book is if you reread it (and how many times).</em></p>
<p><em>We ask “why is he rich (or poor)?” not “why isn’t he richer (or poorer)?”; “why is the crisis so deep?” not “why isn’t it deeper?”</em></p>
<p><em>Most people fear being without audiovisual stimulation because they are too repetitive when they think and imagine things on their own.</em></p>
<p><em>The book is the only medium left that hasn’t been corrupted by the profane. Everything else on your eyelids manipulates you with an ad.</em></p>
<p><em>To be completely cured of newspapers, spend a year reading the previous week’s newspapers.</em></p>
<p><em>Fortune punishes the greedy by making him poor and the very greedy by making him rich.</em></p>
<p><em>“Wealthy” is meaningless and has no robust absolute measure; use instead the subtractive measure “unwealth,” that is, the difference, at any point in time, between what you have and what you would like to have.</em></p>
<p><em>Someone who says “I am busy” is either declaring incompetence (and lack of control of his life) or trying to get rid of you.</em></p>
<p><em>You are rich if and only if money you refuse tastes better than money you accept.</em></p>
<p><em>People focus on role models; it is more effective to find antimodels — people you don’t want to resemble when you grow up.</em></p>
<p><em>Over the long term, you’re more likely to fool yourself than others.</em></p>
<p><em>There are two types of people: those who try to win and those who try to win arguments. They are never the same.</em></p>
<p><em>We are hunters; we are only truly alive in those moments when we improvise; no schedule, just small surprises and stimuli from the environment.</em></p>
<p><em>The three most harmful addictions are heroin, carbohydrates, and a monthly salary.</em></p>
<p><em>It’s much harder to write a book review for a book you’ve read than for a book you haven’t read.</em></p>
<p><em>Robust is when you care more about the few who like your work than the multitude who dislike it (artist); fragile when you care more about the few who dislike your work than the multitude who like it (politicians).</em></p>
<p><em>They think that intelligence is about noticing things that are relevant (detecting patterns); in a complex world, intelligence consists in ignoring things that are irrelevant (avoiding false patterns). </em><em>[Corollary: The best way to spot a charlatan: someone (like a consultant or a stock-broker) who tells you what to do instead of what not to do.]</em></p>
<p><em>A prophet is not someone with special visions, just someone blind to most of what others see.</em></p>
<p><em>What organized dating sites fail to understand is that people are far more interesting in what they don’t say about themselves.</em></p>
<p><em>A good foe is far more loyal, far more predictable, and, to the clever, far more useful than the most valuable admirer.</em></p>
<h4>Parting Thoughts</h4>
<p>Being a parent, the sentence that shook me the hardest was about the procrustean methods that society is thrusting on our kids. Taleb writes —</p>
<blockquote><p>Few realize that we are changing the brains of schoolchildren through medication in order to make them adjust to the curriculum, rather than the reverse.</p></blockquote>
<p>Having experienced (intermittently) the luxury of freedom from conventional 9-to-5 routine, I could relate to what Taleb wrote as the closing sentence of the book.</p>
<blockquote><p>By setting oneself totally free of this debilitating activity called work, elements hidden in the texture of reality start staring at you; then mysteries that you never thought existed emerge in front of your eyes.</p></blockquote>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../unnerving-words-of-an-idiosyncratic-genius/index.html">Unnerving Words of an Idiosyncratic Genius</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="./../../../index.html">Anshul Khare</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>./../../../unnerving-words-of-an-idiosyncratic-genius/feed/index.html</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<post-id xmlns="com-wordpress:feed-additions:1">466</post-id>	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
